We finished yesterday's discussion and yesterday's discussion was actually quite fascinating because
אביי Abaye collected a number of different תנאים, Tannaim, a number of
different positions in various משניות Mishnayot that all from אביי's Abaye perspective
made greater requirements of a סוכה Sukkah that reflects an understanding of
a סוכה Sukkah as דירת קבע, Dirat Keva, as a more permanent
structure. And as we said, this is part of the whole question
of a סוכה, Sukkah, because a סוכה Sukkah on the one hand
is the difference between your house, your house is permanent, your סוכה
Sukkah is temporary. On the other hand, your סוכה Sukkah is a
substitute for your house, so it has to maybe be more house-like.
So אביי Abaye identified a number of positions where each one might
have its own unique reason, but they could all be seen as
rooted in the idea of סוכה Sukkah as a permanent structure, but
maybe how that idea of greater permanence translates is interpreted differently by
the different תנאים. Tannaim. So let's actually pick up from that very
quickly again from the beginning, and it'll just I guess more
in the middle of ז' עמוד ב', Zayin Amud Bet, but we'll
do it quickly, we had done half of it yesterday. So it's
about 20 lines down, line starts with the words דמכסי כסכך.
demachsi
keschach.
So אמר אביי: Amar Abaye:
So is it the סכך schach that makes it the concept of
temporary dwelling in terms of the idea?
Oh, yes, well that is true, meaning even those that say that
it's more permanent, and thank you for pointing that out, you know
תוספות Tosafot said you could have permanent walls but you can't have
a permanent roof. Roof, that, so it's a good point, according to
those that say that it is more permanent, what distinguishes it from
your house? Now we're going to see something at the end of
today's דף, daf, God willing we'll get there, that it might just
be your usage. Maybe structurally it could be identical and maybe the
only difference is whether you use it during the year or not.
But what you're saying is probably correct, that no matter who says
it's a permanent structure or you know the סכך schach remains temporary
and remains what fundamentally distinguishes it. Presumably nobody disagrees with that and
that was a תוספות Tosafot we did at the very beginning. Yes,
so thank you for pointing that out. אמר אביי רבי ורבי יאשיה
ורבי יהודה ורבי שמעון ורבי שמעון בן גמליאל רבי שמעון בן גמליאל
בית שמאי ורבי אליעזר ואחרים כולם סבירא להו סוכה דירת קבע בעינן.
Amar Abaye: Rabbi, ve-Rabbi Yoshiya, ve-Rabbi Yehuda, ve-Rabbi Shimon, ve-Rabbi Shimon ben
Gamliel, Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel, Beit Shammai, ve-Rabbi Eliezer, ve-acherim kulu sevira
lehu sukkah dirat keva beinan.
They all say סוכה sukkah in some way is a permanent structure
or to some degree permanent and that's reflected in a certain requirement,
but each one sort of you know translates that into different requirements.
רבי דתניא רבי אומר כל סוכה שאין בה ארבע על ארבע אמות
פסולה. Rabbi de-tanya: Rabbi omer kol sukkah she-ein bo arba al arba
amot psulah. It has to be four by four אמות, amot, not
ראשו ורובו rosho ve-rubo and ושולחנו, ve-shulchano, not seven טפחים. tefachim. It
has to be a more serious size. רבי יאשיה הא דאמרן, Rabbi
Yoshiya ha de-amaran, רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya who says the walls have
to provide shade. What's a house that has transparent walls? No, to
be a serious you know have more permanence and be a more
serious house-like, the walls have to provide shade as well. רבי יהודה
דתנן סוכה שהיא גבוהה למעלה מעשרים אמה פסולה ורבי יהודה מכשיר. Rabbi
Yehuda de-tnan: Sukkah she-hi gevovah lemala me-esrim ammah psulah ve-Rabbi Yehuda machshir.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows a סוכה sukkah higher than twenty אמות.
amot. So that's got to be more permanent and he allows it.
He doesn't require it, that's why this is a little bit different,
as opposed to the others who require it, here it's just רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows it. רבי שמעון דתניא בראשונה ושתים והשלישית אפילו
טפח, Rabbi Shimon de-tanya: be-rishona u-shtayim ve-hashlishit afilu tefach, two and a
bit, two walls and a little bit is the requirement. רבי שמעון
אומר ג' כהלכתן וד' אפילו טפח, Rabbi Shimon omer: gimel ke-hilchatan ve-dalet
afilu tefach, three walls and a little bit. So that's a requirement
that makes it more of a serious permanent structure or more house-like.
Okay, and it's similar it should be mentioned to the רבי יאשיה
Rabbi Yoshiya who demands the walls provide shade. They're demanding not just
סכך schach and the walls are very secondary, you want the walls
to serve a more house-like function. Either they have to surround you
more, three and a bit, or they have to shade, and those
are ways in which it's more house-like. רבן גמליאל דתניא, Rabban Gamliel
de-tanya, and now so those are תנאים Tannaim we've already seen and
now new תנאים. Tannaim. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel because we taught a
ברייתא, braita, so it's not just a משנה mishnah now that we're
looking at. העושה סוכתו בראש העגלה או בראש הספינה, Ha-oseh sukkato be-rosh
ha-agalah o be-rosh ha-sefinah, actually רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya also wasn't, a
lot of these weren't משניות, mishnayot, they were
ברייתות. braitot. If you make a סוכה sukkah at the top of
a wagon on the wagon like a Chabad sort of you know
you know sort of portable סוכה, sukkah, סוכה sukkah
mobile, or on the top of a boat, רבן גמליאל פוסל ורבי
עקיבא מכשיר. Rabban Gamliel posel ve-Rabbi Akiva machshir. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
says it's no good, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's good. Why
shouldn't it be good? And the reason it's not good is because
it's less stable. Now תוספות Tosafot has a question whether they also
whether the wagon example should be here. The boat in the גמרא
Gemara in particular is an issue because the winds on the ocean
are much stronger than on the dry land. So it won't be
able to stand up to the winds on the ocean even though
it could stand up if it remains in the port. And the
wagon also might be part of the debate depending on if you
have that גירסא girsa here. Because also you know it bounces around
and it's less stable and it could fall apart. So something that
is more its you know stability is more precarious that is debated.
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says no good, it has to be more
stable.
בית שמאי דתנן מי שהיה ראשו ורובו בסוכה ושולחנו בתוך הבית בית
שמאי פוסלין ובית הלל מכשירין.
Beit Shammai de-tnan: Mi
she-haya rosho ve-rubo ba-sukkah ve-shulchano be-toch ha-bayit Beit Shammai poslin ve-Beit Hillel
machshirin. The debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit
Shammai whether a סוכה sukkah has to contain just your head and
your body or your head and your body and your table. Now
that does not seem like a big difference right? That seems like
okay. עראי arai but it still has to be a דירה. dirah.
If your table's in the house or it's not big enough for
your table, you're not even going to be temporarily there, you're always
going to be running after your table. So again, they're not all
to the same degree, but everybody here makes greater demands of some
sense of stability and permanence and so on. Although conceptually you would
have put בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai roughly
in the same category and just disagreeing on degree, nevertheless at least
רבי Rebbe here's saying בית שמאי Beis Shammai is more in this
direction of permanence. Of course we פוסקין pasken like בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai, so but that doesn't necessarily mean we פוסקין pasken סוכה Sukkah
is a permanent dwelling because again בית שמאי Beis Shammai is the
least of these תנאים Tannaim that make these demands.
Okay.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer תנן. tnan. How about רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
because we talked? העושה סוכתו כמין צריף, Ha'oseh sukkaso k'min tzrif, עושה
סוכה, oseh sukkah, if you make your סוכה Sukkah like a teepee.
או שסומכה לכותל, O she'samcha l'kotel, or רש״י Rashi actually says it
might not just be a teepee, it might also
be something sort of like a yurt, I think, if I remember
what a yurt is, but it's basically maybe more like an igloo
where, I think igloo is the better example, where the roof is
a continuation of the walls, and there's not a clear line, here
are the walls, here's the roof. Okay, so you make it a
teepee, an igloo, or a lean-to, a lean-to is סומכה לכותל. somcha
l'kotel. So all of those you know you could maybe הלכתית halachically
imagine that part of the wall is a roof, but it doesn't
structurally really have the clear line of what's the walls, what's the
roof. רבי אליעזר פוסל לפי שאין לה גג,
Rabbi Eliezer posel lefi
she'ain la gag, there's no structural roof even if there's a הלכתי
halachic roof, and it's not good. וחכמים מכשירין Vachachamim machshirim and the
חכמים Chachamim say it's okay. So again the demand for something to
be more house-like,
with a real distinguishable roof and walls is אביי Abaye putting it
in the similar category. Again, whether all of this is about קבע,
keva, permanence, not all of these is about the concept of permanence.
Some of these might be like I'm saying more of a concept
of house-like, but nevertheless אביי Abaye putting all these together, all these
תנאים Tannaim have demands of a סוכה Sukkah that it be more
house-like and more in that direction. Three walls, three and, I mean
three and a half walls, the walls provide shade, it has to
be bigger, four by four, has to have a distinguishable roof. All
of these things are roughly in this position that a סוכה Sukkah
has to be more קבע, keva, more house-like. אחרים, acherim, how about
others, which is usually רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? דתניא, detanya, we taught
in the ברייתא, Braitah, אחרים אומרים סוכה העשויה כשובך פסולה לפי שאין
לה זוויות. Acherim omrim sukkah asuya k'shuvach pesulah lefi she'ein la zaviyot.
If you have a circular סוכה, Sukkah, it is invalid, even if
it's got a normal roof, but if it's a circle it's invalid
because it doesn't have corners. Who lives in a circular house? Okay
that's the yurt I guess, but anyway normal people live in houses
with angles and walls and a distinguishable roof and so on. So
that is not a normal type of a place that people live
and therefore no good. So each one of these maybe has a
different articulation of how this translates הלכתית, halachically, but they want a
סוכה Sukkah to be more house-like. Now it should be known that
there's a general principle in הלכה halacha
that
when a גמרא Gemara says, this is not uncommon, that an אמורא
Amora says all of these תנאים Tannaim all hold this שיטה, shittah,
okay, that A, it's a fascinating right collecting them together and trying
to see them as coming from a similar approach, there's an importance
obviously in that beyond the question of הלכה, halacha, but there tends
to be a הלכתי halachic assumption that when the גמרא Gemara does
that, it's coming to say we don't פוסקין pasken like it. It's
coming to almost bracket them out and say, yeah they're all coming
from this approach that's not the approach we go by. Now the
גמרא Gemara doesn't say that here, but it's just interesting to know
that there's an idea that when the גמרא Gemara says שיטה אחת,
shittah achas, that it's to be pushed away from הלכה. halacha. Again
not clear from what we read but that tends to be a
הלכתי halachic assumption. Okay. Now that we've mentioned a circular סוכה, Sukkah,
we're going to move into some real fun discussion about geometry. So
everybody who loved geometry in high school, okay, this is the גמרא
Gemara that they really love, everybody who hated it, okay stick with
me. All right, I'm not going to say I'm going to be
better than your geometry teacher, but let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבי יוחנן סוכה העשויה ככבשן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, sukkah asuya k'kivshan, if a סוכה Sukkah is made like
a furnace, meaning it's a circular סוכה, Sukkah, אם יש בהיקפה כדי
לישב בה עשרים וארבעה בני אדם, im yesh b'hekefa k'dei le'sheiv ba
esrim v'arba b'nei adam, if in its circumference there is enough for
twenty four people to sit, כשרה, kesherah, ואם לאו פסולה v'im lav
pesulah and if not it's invalid.
Now we have to make some assumptions. First of all the minimum
size of a סוכה, Sukkah, the way we פוסקין, pasken, is seven
טפחים tefachim by seven טפחים. tefachim. You do not need, there's no
way you're going to need twenty four people to sit in a
circular סוכה Sukkah to fit seven טפחים tefachim by seven טפחים. tefachim.
At seven טפחים tefachim is about what, two feet by two feet.
Twenty four people is going to be a lot more than a
two foot by two foot square. So the first assertion the גמרא
Gemara makes is כמאן כרבי דאמר כל סוכה שאין בה ארבע אמות
על ארבע אמות פסולה. k'man k'Rebbi, d'amar kol sukkah she'ein ba arba
amos al arba amos pesulah.
We first have to be starting with an assumption that your minimum
סוכה Sukkah is a larger one. So the
feet by
six feet, okay. Now, twenty-four people sitting in six feet by six
feet, right, it would seem that that's maybe a little a lot,
right? So,
if you imagine roughly a person, you know, was in like a
foot, a foot and a half depending if you're trying to fit
on a New York subway, you know, seat or whatever, the גמרא
Gemara imagines a normal person sits in an אמה. amah. So I'm
going to drop feet, I just wanted it to rule stick with
אמות, amos, but I just wanted to give you the imagination an
אמה's amah about a foot and a half. How big do they
make the seats on the New York subway? Maybe a foot and
a half.
Four by four is sixteen.
What? Right, exactly. So if you imagine that a person sits in
an אמה amah by an אמה, amah, okay, then that's sixteen. Where
are you getting twenty-four? Not big enough. What?
Not big enough, big enough.
Yeah, I know. It's big enough on the New York subway. Right,
so the... anyway that's the גמרא's Gemara assumption about an אמה amah
by an אמה. amah. But anyway I'm just kidding. I mean if
you sit tight, right, that's like New York City subway. Okay, anyway.
So let's see why you need twenty-four. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so מכדי, mikhdi, let's figure this out, says the גמרא, Gemara, let's
see. גברא באמתא יתיב, gavra be'amsa yatev, if a person sits in
an אמה, amah, meaning like an אמה amah by an אמה amah
as we'll see that'll be important later. כל שיש בהיקפו שלשה טפחים,
kol she'yesh beheikefo sheloshah tefachim,
anything that the circumference is three, יש בו רוחב טפח, yesh bo
rocheve tefach, the width, meaning the diameter is one, meaning what is
the proportion of circumference to diameter? Pi, right?
Does anybody remember? Right?
Pi equals
two R, wait no I'm sorry.
Circumference equals two pi R. No that's area, this is circumference, okay?
Two R is diameter, so circumference equals pi times diameter, right? Pi
times diameter, which is another way of saying pi is the ratio
of the circumference to the diameter. Yes? Okay, so here's your circle,
your circumference, that's your diameter, the ratio of circumference to diameter is
what pi is. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara estimates pi at three.
All right, we're not going to do that. There's another גמרא Gemara
that learns it out from from the sort of big bath that
they had in the time of שלמה, Shlomo, not that whatever anyway,
the big immersion pool in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but we're
not going to worry about that, the גמרא Gemara estimates it as
three. Okay? So the גמרא's Gemara saying anything that has a diameter
one has a circumference of three. Three is our estimate of pi.
All right, so that's what the גמרא Gemara starts by saying. כל
שיש בהיקפו שלשה, kol she'yesh beheikefo sheloshah, or it says the other
way, anything that has a circumference of three, יש בו רוחב טפח,
yesh bo rocheve tefach,
has a diameter of one. So בתריסר סגי, bitreisar sagi, says the
גמרא Gemara starts by circling, saying if your סוכה sukkah needs to
be four אמות, amos, so four is the height, right, if it
needs to be four אמות, amos, then the circumference of it should
only have to be a twelve circumference. You have four אמות, amos,
four times three is a twelve circumference. Why do you need twenty-four?
The answer to that is obvious because you don't fit a four
by four square into that, that's the widest point of four, but
that's the גמרא's Gemara first question. Okay, why if it's four אמות,
amos, so you have a diameter of four אמות amos and now
your circumference will be twelve. בתריסר סגי, bitreisar sagi, twelve should be
enough. גמרא Gemara says no, הני מילי בעיגולא, hanei milei be'igula, it's
true, you're in a if you're dealing with a circle, so if
you had a four diameter, you would only need a twelve circumference
circle, right, if you know that's what you would have. But when
we say a סוכה sukkah has to be four, we don't mean
at its widest point, we mean four by four, although
בריבוע בעי טפי, beribua ba'ei tefei, but we need a square of
four by four. Okay, so how big does the circle have to
be to fit inside of it a square of four by four?
Is that clear what we're trying to get at? Yes? Your סוכה
sukkah to be four by four, a circle has to fit a
square inside of it of four by four. So the גמרא Gemara
says מכדי, mikhdi, let's take a look. כמה מרובע יתר על העיגול
רביע. kama meruba yoser al ha'igul reviya. How much bigger is a
circle is a square than a circle? It is a quarter. What
does this mean? It means that the גמרא Gemara is first going
to be looking at a circle in a square. Really should be
looking at a square in a circle, we'll get to that in
a minute, but it's first going to look at a circle in
a square. Squaring off the circle. Now so whatever, you get the
idea. What is the ratio of the circumference of the circle to
the circumference of the square? Well, if this is one, right, or
let's call this
diameter, thank you, diameter, the
circle's circumference is three D, right, three times diameter because we're estimating
pi at three. What's the circumference of the square? D squared?
No. Circumference of the square, four D, right, each side of it's
D, right? 4D. So the square is a quarter bigger, I mean
a quarter of this, or the circle is a quarter less of
the circumference of the square. Okay, so that's the line in the
גמרא Gemara which says, let's read that again. מכדי. Michdi. כמה ריבוע
יותר על העיגול? Kama ribu'a yoseir al ha'igul? How much bigger is
the circumference of the square to the circle? רביע. Revi'a. It is
a quarter bigger, meaning if it's four, the circle inside of it
is three.
בשיתסרי. Be'shis-sa-rei. So the גמרא Gemara says, now obviously this is,
it's funny that it makes assumptions, but it says like this, it
says, okay, so if you had a, what's the circumference that you
need of a square 4x4?
What's the circumference of a square that's 4x4?
16. Okay, and the 16 circumference, right? That's circumference of or circumference
equals 16. So the גמרא Gemara says, we've just proven that a
circle that has a width of four has a circumference of 12.
So the square that has a width of four has a circumference
of 16. Okay, it could have done it easier. Could have just
said a square 4x4 has a circumference of 16. But since we've
been starting with the circle and we said if this is four,
the circumference is 12, it says, oh, well, the square is a
quarter bigger, so the square is 16. So why, says the גמרא,
Gemara, let's have the circle that we demand just have the same
circumference of the square. Okay, that's a little complicated but basically the
way it's saying is, we need a square 4x4, right? The circumference
of a square 4x4 is 16. Okay, that's the point it says.
It's 12, from 12 you get 16, the circumference is 16 anyway,
it's obvious, circumference of a square 4x4 is 16. Okay, so then
the גמרא Gemara says, fine, so if you're making a circle סוכה,
sukkah, just have it have a circumference of 16. Why do you
need a circumference of 24? Take the circumference and make the circle
have the same circumference. Okay, and the גמרא's Gemara answer is, no,
that's not what you need to do.
Okay, הני מילי בעיגול דנפיק מגו ריבוע, Hani milei bi-igul de-nafik mi-go
ribu'a, if the circle's in the square, so then the square around
it would have a circumference of 16 in this example if the
circle had a circumference of 12. But we don't just want to
say what, imagine that like the circumference of the square around it,
we need to get the circle to contain a square. אבל ריבוע
דנפיק מגו עיגול בעי טפי. Aval ribu'a de-nafik mi-go igul ba'ei tfei.
And that again is here, this is, so that's the idea that
the outer square is a 3:4 ratio, okay, we'll just do that
here to remember that point, okay, so the first point we made
is that the ratio of the sort of circumference here, right, the
circumference of the circle, the circumference of the circle, whatever.
Anyway, the circumference here is three, then the circumference of the square
is four. That's a 3:4 ratio, okay, of the circumference. But the
גמרא Gemara says we're not interested in a square around a circle,
we're interested in your סוכה sukkah here is a circle and you
need to fit a square סוכה sukkah in
your current circle. So you have a circle and we have to
say it has to be big enough to fit a square that
is 4x4 into the סוכה. sukkah. Okay, now, can you figure out,
any good people who were good at geometry,
what type of square you need to fit a, what type of
circle you need to square a 4x4? We have to draw a
line,
we have to figure out what is the diameter.
Okay, what's the diameter of the circle? What is the diameter?
The diagonal of the square is the diameter of the circle. What's
the diagonal of the square?
Yeah, it's 4 times, right, everybody remember your Pythagorean theorem, 4 times
the square root of 2, right? A squared plus b squared equals
c squared, so the diagonal of if you have a and b
are the same, the diagonal is 4 times the square root of
2. That is the circumference of the circle, okay, and therefore that's
the diameter of the circle, and therefore the circumference is going to
have to be three, like it's three times the
diameter, three times 4 times the square root of 2. What? Square
root of 32? I don't know, it's 12 times the square root
of 2. It's going to be three times 4 times the square
root of 2. Okay, so let's take a look. That's what the
גמרא's Gemara going to do, okay? The גמרא Gemara says like this:
'Okay,
מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look. כל אמתא בריבועא אמתא ותרי חומשי
באלכסונא.
Kol amsa be-ribu'a amsa ve-trei
chumshai be-alakhsona. כל
אמתא בריבועא, Kol amsa be-ribu'a, any thing that's an אמה amah squared,
you know, an אמה amah by an אמה, amah, a square that's
an אמה amah by an אמה, amah, אמתא ותרי חומשי באלכסונא amsa
ve-trei chumshai be-alakhsona is one and two-fifths, 1.4 in the diagonal. So
anything that is 1x1 has a diagonal of 1.4, which means 1.4
is the גמרא's Gemara estimate of the diagonal... yeah. But of the
square root of two. Okay? It’s saying that the basic ratio here
of a one by one, the diagonal is. Do people remember why
this is true? Yes, a squared plus b squared equals c squared.
So if a and b are the same, it’s 2a squared equals
c squared, right?
So whatever, doesn't matter. Okay, a one by one has a diagonal
of 1.4. So the גמרא Gemara is estimating it as 1.4, which
is actually not pretty accurate. Much better than three being pi. The
square root of two is like 1.414.
Okay. So that’s actually quite close, to make it 1.4. So the
גמרא Gemara says the diagonal here will be 1.4 times the side.
Okay. So if that’s true,
so בשבסר נכי חומשא סגיא, bishivsar naki chumsha sagya, you should get
to seventeen minus a fifth. Meaning, what’s four times 1.4?
5.6.
Okay. That’s the diameter. So therefore the circumference, that’s the diameter. So
the circumference is going to be three times that, right? Pi times
the diameter is three times 5.6 equals what? 16.8. Okay.
That’s still not 24, which is what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said.
So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
בשבסר נכי חומשא סגיא. bishivsar naki chumsha sagya. So 17 minus the
fifth, meaning 16.8 should be enough. So why did he say 24?
We got you. Finally we got to the idea that it have
to be the square in the circle. But the square in the
circle of four by four only leads to a circle of 16.8
of a circumference. Why is he saying 24? So the גמרא Gemara
says לא דק. lo dak. He’s not being so precise. So the
גמרא Gemara says אימור דאמרינן לא דק, eimar d'amrinan lo dak, when
you say not precise, פורתא, pursa, a little bit, you round off.
טובא מי אמרינן? tuva mi amrinan? To go from 16.8 to 24?
Oh, he’s not being precise. Whoever says such a huge gap is
not precise? He’s rounding off to the nearest 24? Okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says, so מי אמרינן לא דק? mi amrinan
lo dak? אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב אשי, amar
lei Mar Kashisha brei d'Rav Chisda l'Rav Ashi, מי סברת גברא באמתא
יתיב? mi savrat gavra b'amta yasiv? אנא, ana, here’s how we’re going
to get 24 people. Who told you that a person sits in
an אמה? amah? תלתא גברי בתרי אמתא יתבי, tlasa gavri b’trei amasa
yasiv, three people to two אמות. amot. Okay, that’s basically a foot
per person. Okay? So basically three people in every two אמות. amot.
So if that’s true, three people in every two אמות, amot, let’s
figure out what we’re going to get. Instead of four people, four
אמות amot by four, right?
Four by four, well maybe it’s just easier to work with this.
If it’s 16.8 אמות, amot, how many people is that? So if
it’s three people for every two, you divide by, you multiply it
by one and a half, right? You divide by two and three
people. Okay, so what is that times one and a half? What’s
16.8 times one and a half? Half of that is 8.4.
We’re going to get 25.2.
Is that right? Yeah, okay, 24, 25.2, yeah. Okay. So basically that’s
what you’d get. So 16.8 אמות amot according to three people for
every two אמות amot is 25.2 people. Okay, but he said 24.
So it’s a lot closer. Let’s take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so, okay,
כמה הוי להו? kama havei lehu? שיתסר. shit-sar. אנן, anan, so how
many people would you need to get 24? It does the math
that way. Sixteen. Okay, it does the math the other way, which
is, which is,
if you have 16 people,
and
three people for every two אמות, amot, so how many אמות amot
does 16 people get you? Does 16, did I say this right?
No, I’m sorry. I’m sorry.
If you had 16 אמות, amot, how many people would you need
for 16 to fit in 16 אמות? amot? It would be three
people for every two אמות. amot. So it would be 24, right?
Because it’s times one and a half. So you would need 24
people. So we have said, so רבי יוחנן’s Rabbi Yochanan 24 people
translates to,
no, 24 people, three people in every two אמות. amot. Okay. So
רבי יוחנן’s, Rabbi Yochanan here’s it says 24 people would mean we’re
dealing with a circumference of 16 אמות. amot. Whereas we’ve determined that
we need a circumference of 16.8 אמות. amot. But we’re a lot
closer. 24 people with assuming three for every two leads to a
אמה amah circumference.
Okay. So that’s what the גמרא Gemara says.
And so therefore, so
therefore רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan 24 אמות, amot, according
to this, 24 people according to this would create a circumference, a
circle of 16 אמות. amot. 24 will not create 24, 24 will
create 16.
And we came to the conclusion of 16 that you needed a
circle of 16.8 according to your new math, right, your circumference is
only 16. So how could that be? How could that work? לא
דק. Lo dak. All right, he's being imprecise. Okay. Yeah, 24 will
only get you 16, you really need a little bit more. You
really need 16.8.
So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, אימר דאמרינן לא דק.
eimar de'amrinan lo dak. When can we say you're being a little
imprecise? לחומרא. Lechumra. If you're rounding up לחומרא. lechumra. לקולא מי אמרינן
לא דק? Lekula mi amrinan lo dak? We wouldn't say it לקולא.
lekula. Right? If you say you only need 24 people, you're going
to have a סוכה, sukkah, you're going to have a circumference of
16 אמות. amot. That's not big enough. You need a circumference of
16.8 אמות. amot. So we can't say, yeah, you're being imprecise. Be
imprecise and tell us you need a little more, not a little
less. 24 is going to lead to a סוכה sukkah that's too
small. So even in your new math that it's three for every
two, you're not going to get to the right answer, which is
16.8 אמות. amot. What did you want to say? Two people I
had yesterday. Yeah, well that's also true. You have to be an
average person. You have to balance the heavy ones with the thin
ones. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, so we're still stuck.
So let's take a look. אמרי ליה רב אסי לרב אשי. Amrei
lei Rav Assi le-Rav Ashi. לעולם גברא באמה יתבי. Le-olam gavra be-amah
yatvei. Forget this new math. One person per אמה. amah. Okay. Now,
so one person per אמה, amah, we're back to the problem that
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said 24 people, which is 24 אמות, amot,
and the circle that we need is only 16.8 אמות. amot. So
again, how does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan match up? We're back to
one person per אמה. amah. So, רבי יוחנן מקום גברי לא קחשיב.
Rabbi Yochanan mekom gavrei lo kachshiv. He's not counting the place where
people are sitting. What does that mean? It means רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is not assuming people are sitting on the inside. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is assuming that people are sitting on the outside. They're
sitting around your סוכה, sukkah, not on the inner circumference of your
circle. So if they're sitting around your סוכה, sukkah, how big, right,
is, if they're sitting here, right? The people are sitting here, and
they're creating an around, they're sitting on the outside around your סוכה.
sukkah. How much bigger do you need that circle to be if
you're now going to measure from the backs of the people? So
you're going to be adding here to the diameter. How much are
you adding to the diameter? Two אמות. amot. Each person is an
אמה amah by an אמה. amah. So people are sitting around your
סוכה, sukkah, right? And now you're going to measure the circle from
their backs. So you're going to have a new diameter that's no
longer, right, 5.26, but your new diameter is going to be 7.26.
Is that clear? Yes? Pretty much? Okay. So now that we're sitting
outside and around, the new circle created, measured from behind us, is
7.26 diameter, which is going to be how much of a circumference?
21, 18, 22.8, which is pretty close, right, to the
24. Yeah?
Okay. No, it's better.
We're better. And we're being, and we're rounding off לחומרא. lechumra. All
right. So let's take a look.
רבי יוחנן מקום גברי לא קחשיב. Rabbi Yochanan mekom gavrei lo kachshiv.
He's not counting the space that the people are sitting in, meaning
they're sitting on the outside. It's basically what it means. כמה הוי
להו? Kama havei lehu? תמני סרי. Temani srei. So, oh, 18. Hold
on.
I got that wrong. How is it 18? Wait
a minute. Wait. I think I said, hold on a minute. Hold
on, I think I said this wrong. Wait a minute. מאחורי
דמקום תאמר דהכי דאמרי דאכמן וחשבון מרווח העיגול שתי אמות על שתי
אמות שכשאתה סובבו מבחוץ מבחוץ
ההיקף עשרים וארבע אתה
מוצא בתוכו שמונה על שמונה. me-achurei de-makom tomar de-hachi de-amri de-achman ve-cheshbon
merovach ha-igul shetei amot al shetei amot she-ke-she-ata sovevo mi-bachutz, mi-bachutz ha-heikef
esrim
ve-arba, ata
motze be-tocho shemonah al shemonah. וכל שיש בהיקפו
שלשה יש בו רוחב
טפח.
ve-chol she-yesh be-heikefo
sheloshah yesh bo
rochav
tefach.
One
minute.
Okay. That's for the eight diameter. שדפנה מבפנים משיבה אינה רוחב אלא
ששה על ששה. she-dafenah mi-bi-fanim mi-meshiva einah rochav ela shishah al shishah.
דגברא באמה יתבי. de-gavra be-amah
yatvei. And והכא באשב v'hacha b'ashav שדפנותיו
מפנימה למושבו אינו רחב אלא ששה ששה. she-dafanotav mipnima le-moshavo eno rachav
ela shisha shisha. I'm
fixed.
That's how we got the six. What? Six and three. But where
do you get six?
Hold on, hold on.
This made sense last night. Hold on. רבי יוחנן מקום גברא לא
חשיב Rabbi Yochanan makom gavra lo chashiv ותוספות סותר v'tosafo soter רבי
יוחנן מקום גברא לא חשיב ותוספות סותר
רבי יוחנן מקום גברא לא חשיב ותוספות סותר דלא חשיב לא מקום
אדם ולא השם ולא
המשירה ובפרק מעיקרא.
v'tosafo
soter
Rabbi Yochanan makom gavra lo
chashiv v'tosafo soter Rabbi Yochanan
makom gavra lo chashiv v'tosafo
soter de-lo chashiv lo makom
adam ve-lo hashem ve-lo hameshira
u-veperek
m'ikor.
Where was I getting six? What? Three people for two אמות? amot?
No, we dropped the three people for two אמות, amot, that would
be lower. Right.
רשי Rashi says if you start this with six, right, then 6
plus 2 is 8, right? 6 plus 2 is right, 6 plus
2 is 8, that gets you 24.
So that's being imprecise though, because that's demanding that to be six
rather than 5.6. So oh, that's what the גמרא Gemara means. Okay
fine. Alright, now I got it. Okay, here's the point. If we
say 24 people, okay, this you have to work backwards. If we
say 24 people standing on the outside, that means a diameter of
eight, right? To get 24, against the 3.1. Which means, and you
subtract the one at both ends, that means a diameter of six
on the inner circle. Okay? And if you have a diameter of
six on the inner circle, your circumference on the inner circle is
18. Okay? Right? You see that? So if you, if this is
24, then that's 8, if that's 8 then this is 6, and
then therefore the circumference is 18. So by creating an outer circle
of 24, it leads to a circle that has a circumference of
18. Whereas we said you only needed a circumference of 16.8. Okay?
So let's see, so let's take a look. So it says, that's
what the גמרא Gemara is saying. So it says, רבי יוחנן מקום
גברא לא חשיב. Rabbi Yochanan makom gavra lo chashiv. So כמה הוי
להו? kama havei lehu? So how much of does the 24 people,
what type of a circumference does it translate into in terms of
the inner circle? כמה נשתייר? kam nishrei? 18. So and we said
בשית עשר וחומישא סגי, be-shis-asar ve-chumsha sagi, you only needed 16.8. גמרא
Gemara says, היינו לא דק ולחומרא לא דק. haynu lo daka ve-le-chumra
lo daka. Oh, now we're on safer territory. Now we can say
he was being imprecise, but he was being מחמיר machmir imprecise, not
מיקל. meikil. You need 24 people on the outside, which leads to
an inside which is a little bit bigger than you need. You
really only need an inside square of 5.6, he's going to get
you an inside square of 6. He's going to be a little
bit more מחמיר. machmir. 24 on the outside gets you 18 on
the inside gets you 6. Okay, so that's where now we're done.
Now we figured it out. רבנן דקיסרי Rabbanan de-Kesari ואמרי לה דייני
דקיסרי, ve-amri lei dayyane de-Kesari, the Rabbis of Caesarea, and some say
the judges of Caesarea, אמרי, amri, they say: עיגולא דנפיק מגו ריבועא
ריבעא, igula de-nafik mi-go ribu'a riv'a, like we said before, a circle
inside of the square is a quarter, meaning it's a three to
four ratio. But ריבועא דנפיק מגו עיגולא, ribu'a de-nafik mi-go igula, but
the square that's out of coming out of the circle, ריבוע ribu'a
case, פלגא palga is half. Okay? Now that is crazy, because as
we've been seeing, the square inside the circle is pretty close. Okay,
let's even talk about what is the general ratio, right? The square,
here, if a circle is in the square, the circle has a
circumference of three and the square has a circumference of four. What
is it the other way around? What's the ratio of the square
inside the circle? Whatever. Okay, imagine that that's a square. Alright, anyway,
of the square inside of the circle, right? What's the ratio? So,
here is, if this is one by one, what did we say
the diagonal is? Right? Square root, right, square root of 2. Okay,
let's just do it normal math, okay? That's the diameter. Okay, so
in this case, if a square of one by one is in
a circle, its circumference is going to be four, and the circle's
circumference is going to be... Right? If pi times the square root
of two, right? So pi times the square root of two. Yes,
pi times diameter, right? Which is going to be in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* math, 3 times 1.4, which is 5, 4.2.
So actually, if this is a pretty shocking, it's brilliant if you
think about it, the circle inside the square is a 3 to
4 ratio. The square inside of the circle is much closer in
terms of circumference, 4 to 4.2.
Okay, because it says here, what?
You'll figure it out. Okay. So they say, so the דיינים *Dayanim*
say however, ריבועא דנפיק מגו עיגולא פלגא *Rivuah denafik migo igula palga*
that the square inside of the circle is half. Okay. Now, half
doesn't exactly mean half. Remember what we're trying to do is we're
trying to deal with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabi Yochanan*'s 24. But
what half means here is, is it means a third. It's basically
what רש"י *Rashi* explains what half means. It basically means if you
got this is 24, then this inside is going to be, we
know that you need a סוכה sukkah *sukkah* 4 by 4, right?
Okay, what's the circumference
of that סוכה sukkah *sukkah*? 16, right? 16. So when we say
a half, what we really mean is is that the difference of
16 and 24 is 8, which is half of 16. It's all
complicated. But anyway, basically the way we would say it is is
that it's a ratio of, what's the ratio of 24 to 16?
It's 2 to 3. Okay, they would say it's a 2 to
3 ratio. So if you have 24 on the outside, you got
16 on the inside. We know that the ratio is almost one
to one, okay, not 2 to 3. So they solved it by
saying that the ratio was radically different, and that gets you 16
on the inside. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ולא היא *v'lo
hi*, that's actually not true. דקחזינא דלא הוי כולי האי *d'kachazeina d'la
havi kulei hai*. It says we see that it's not that big.
We see that the ratio is much closer. Okay, but if you
make a bigger ratio, I mean if you assume, you know, that
you need that the סוכה sukkah *sukkah* is three for every two
circumference of the square, a 16 סוכה sukkah. *sukkah* is going to
lead to a 24, circle. Okay, so that's the end of that
סוגיא *sugya*. Now, the fascinating תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* here, which I, which
maybe I'll explain to you, see if I take out a minute
to explain, for those that are not already overwhelmed. But what I
first want to do is tell you what תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* already
realizes and the ראב"ד *Ravad* already realizes is that the דייני דקיסרי
*Dayanei de-Kaysari*, sorry, are right, and they actually did explain רבי יוחנן
*Rabi Yochanan* and probably got the right explanation in רבי יוחנן *Rabi
Yochanan* as opposed to all the complicated outside of the circle that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did. Except they're not talking about circumference. They're
talking about area. What is the ratio, רבי יוחנן *Rabi Yochanan* said
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said רבי יוחנן *Rabi Yochanan* said 24
circumference. But maybe they understood, or maybe there's a different version or
whatever, that they understood he just said 24. And maybe what he
originally said was 24 area. 24 people sit in the סוכה sukkah,
*sukkah*. Right, that makes a lot of sense. You want to talk
about how big it has to be, you talk about how many
people are sitting in the סוכה sukkah *sukkah*. So if he is
saying that your circle סוכה sukkah *sukkah* have to contain, has, if
he is saying that inside it have to contain 24 as an
area, we have to figure out, right, what, we're going to have
to figure out what is the ratio of the area of a
סוכה sukkah *sukkah*, of a circle, to the area of the square
inside of it. Yes? And because the square inside needs, if it's
4 by 4, we know that that's going to lead to an
area of 16. And if a circle that goes around the square
has an area of 24, right, that's the 2 to 3 ratio
we just talked about, then רבי יוחנן *Rabi Yochanan*'s demand of 24
makes sense. If, let's take a look at what is the ratio
of the area of the circle to the area of the square.
So, in this type of a case, right, if this is again
one by one and this is the square root of two, okay,
so what, you know, let's make it even easier. This is 2
by 2 and this is 2 times the square root of two.
Yes? You with me here? What is the radius of that circle
if the diameter is 2 times the square root of two? 1
times
divided by 2. That radius is the square root of two, right?
Yes? You with me? Right? If the diameter is 2 times the
square root of two, the radius is half that. You with me,
yes? Okay, so what is the area of the circle?
Pi R squared, which would be pi times what's R squared?
Two. So, 2 pi. Okay. And if pi is 3, the area
would be 6. What would, what's the area of the square? 2
by 2. 4. What's the ratio of the area of the square
to the area of the circle? Right? 2 to 3. What's, if
a square has a 16 area, what will the סוכה sukkah, *sukkah*'s
area be? 24. Brilliant, right? So simple. People sitting
on the
outside. really it has a sixteen times pi area, but I'm not
doing sixteen times what are we anyway.
Anyway, yeah, but anyway it's no, it has
an eight pi area, right, but eight pi, thank you, but eight
pi is for the גמרא twenty-four. Yes, and that's true. If it's
sixteen on the inside area, the circle around it is twenty-four, and
that's exactly the sort of two to three ratio, right, that the
דייני דקיסריא Dayanei de-Kesarya are talking about. Okay, very nice, brilliant. Why
the גמרא didn't go that way is because the גמרא had clearly
thought that רבי יוחנן was totally talking about circumference and not area.
But at least the דייני דקיסריא, Dayanei de-Kesarya, they got it right
that that is the ratio of the square and the circle if
you're talking about area not circumference. All right, I wanted to tell
you very quickly because you see all these pretty pictures in תוספות,
Tosafos I wanted to just give you a sense of what תוספות
Tosafos is doing. If you look at the עמוד א', Amud Aleph,
first I'm going to do the picture at the very bottom on
the lower left corner.
This is brilliant. This is תוספות's Tosafos demonstration for that one point
four is a little imprecise for the square root of two. It
would have been nice if he would have demonstrated that three is
way imprecise for pi, but he's demonstrating that one point four is
a little imprecise. And here's how he demonstrates it. Imagine a square
ten by
ten. Now he's divided it up into, you know, every little unit.
It's got a hundred on the inside, right? If you see the
picture I'm talking about, you subdivide it to four quarters, each square
is twenty-five, right? Fine. Let's draw a square inside of a square.
Okay, if the outer square is a hundred, how much is the
inner square going to be? It's exactly half, right? It cuts everything
in half, right? So what's the area of the inner square going
to be? Fifty. Yeah, everybody with that? You see how the inner
how that cuts each of the quadrants exactly in half? So the
inner square is going to have to be fifty. Now, let's figure
this out though. If the if in each of those quadrants you
have a side that's five by five and one point four is
supposed to be the hypotenuse, so what's going to be the length
of the diagonal in each of the quadrants? If each of the
quadrants is a five by five square, what's the length of the
diagonal? Five times the square root of two, which is if that's
one point four, five times one point four is come on, it's
not hard
math people, seven! Thank you. So if the square is seven by
seven, what's the area of the square?
Forty-nine, not fifty. So תוספות look, if you use one point four,
you'll get forty-nine when we know that the answer is fifty. So
you see that one point four is a little off. Okay, so
very nice little demonstration that that is a little imprecise for the
square root of two. Now, the other picture is even more fascinating
because the other picture in a way is almost like a little
calculus way before the time of calculus. The other picture wants to
prove the issue about how do you determine the area of a
circle. Okay, and here's how he does it. He says, imagine you
have an infinite amount of lines, right, strings that are making up
a circle. That's this inner picture. All right, now what you're going
to do is you're going to cut all the strings in half,
you're going to you see that little white line? You're going to
cut all the strings in half and lay them out end to
end. That's going to become a triangle that at its base is
the outside string, is the circumference, that's the base of the triangle,
right? And at its height is the radius, because the amount that
you cut. Yes? Is that sort of clear? Because that's yeah. So
therefore, now what is so what is the area of that triangle?
So it's so you've got the diameter of the circle is the
base, you've got the diameter as the base and you've got the
height of the triangle as the right as the radius. Okay, yes?
So but so it's so who remembers what the area of a
triangle is? Base times radius divided by two, right? And the way
תוספות does that is he cuts half of it and he moves
the other half here.
So and he makes it into a rectangle square.
Right. So anyway, so it's diameter
wait base times height no
base times height there's no diameter and radius in the triangle.
I understand, but it's the original diameter radius, right, divided by
two.
Anyway, I don't know, somehow I lost it, but this תוספות *Tosafot*
figures out that... oh, this תוספות *Tosafot* figures out that the math
to get that, I was thinking that תוספות *Tosafot* was just trying
to figure out pi. תוספות *Tosafot* is trying to figure out what's
the calculation for the area of a circle. That's what תוספות *Tosafot*
wants to know, right? You know what, forget it.
Okay. We've had enough math for today.
Alright, moving on. Back to the גמרא *Gemara*. דף ח עמוד ב
*Daf Chet Amud Bet*. אמר רב הונא משום רבי מאיר *Amar Rav
Huna mishum Rabi Meir*: שתי סוכות Sukkos, של צלטרים זו לפנים מזו
*Shtei sukkot shel tzeltarim zu lifnim mi'zu*. If you have two סוכות
Sukkos, *sukkot* of smelters, right, that basically I see you see this
sometimes in these like reconstructed villages from the pilgrim era where they
sort of have like a, you know, a working shop on the
outside and then inside they have like a smaller little sort of
space where the guy lives. On the outside is where he does
the smelting and where he sells his stuff. So the outside is
not actually a living quarters, the living quarters is in the inner
structure. Okay. So you have these two סוכות sukkot, *sukkot*, זו לפנים
מזו *zu lifnim mi'zu*, inner and an outer one. הפנימית אינה סוכה
sukkah *Hapnimis eina sukka*, the inner one can't be used as a
סוכה sukkah *sukka* because that's used for your regular house. Now notice
again this is fascinating, structurally it could be a perfect סוכה sukkah
*sukka*. It's made maybe in a temporary way, it's not a permanent
roof, but nevertheless if it's your house you can't make it your
סוכה sukkah *sukka* if it's the place you generally live. דחייבת במזוזה
*De'hayavet be'mezuza* and because it's your house you have to put a
מזוזה *mezuza* on the inner structure. והחיצונה *Ve'hachitzona*, the outer structure, סוכה
sukkah, *sukka*, you can go ahead and move to your outer structure
for סוכות sukkot. *Sukkot* because that's normally not your house, that's your
shop. Okay. ופטורה מן המזוזה *U'petura min hamuzuza* and it's exempt from
a מזוזה *mezuza* during the in general because you don't normally live
there. Okay. So the גמרא *Gemara* says אמאי *Amai*? גמרא *Gemara*'s only
question here is about the מזוזה *mezuza*. Why is the outer shop
area exempt from a מזוזה *mezuza*? דהוי חיצונית כבית שער הפנימית ותתחייב
במזוזה *De'havei chitzoniyah ke'veit shaar ha'pnimis ve'titchayev be'mezuza*. Let the outer one
be like a gatehouse to the inner one, right? Because if you
have a structure that leads into your house, it's sort of like
an antichamber to your house, then the antichamber requires a מזוזה *mezuza*
as well. So let the outer structure be like a gatehouse to
your house, even if nobody lives there, it should be an entranceway
into your house and also obligated in a מזוזה *mezuza* from the
perspective of your house. גמרא *Gemara* says no, משום דלא קביעא *Mishum
de'lo kvia* because both of these structures, as רש"י *Rashi* understands it,
are not so temporary. So the house is not significant enough to
say that it can have a sort of like a, you know,
an entranceway to it. That idea that an entranceway to a house
requires a מזוזה *mezuza* is by things in which it's natural to
have an entranceway. But something that's such a temporary type of a
structure, we cannot consider the outer part to be an entranceway into
the house like that's for חשוב *chashuv* houses and therefore the outer
part does not demand a מזוזה *mezuza*. So the basic upshot though
is even if something structurally is a סוכה *sukka*, if it's where
you live for the whole year you can't be יוצא *yotzei* סוכה
*sukka* in it. You have to go to your outer room which
is not where you live. Okay. Now we get to a very
interesting idea here about who can make the סוכה *sukka* and what
type of כוונה *kavana* you need. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabbanan*: גנב"ך Ganbakh
*Ganbach*,
if you have a סוכה *sukka* גנב"ך Ganbakh *Ganbach*, it's a mnemonic
that you can remember, it's such a weird mnemonic, which means what?
סוכות גויים *Sukkot goyim*, the סוכה *sukka* made by non-Jews, that's the
ג *Gimel*, סוכות נשים *Sukkot nashim*, or it was made by women,
or סוכות בהמה *Sukkot behema*... I'm sorry, for non-Jews, made by בהמה
*behema* would be interesting... but for and made by seems to also
be... okay, it's sort of both. But okay, but let's I'm sorry,
for non-Jews. For non-Jews, or the non-Jews probably includes made by non-Jews,
or for women, or סוכות בהמה, or for your animals, or סוכות
כותים, Sukkot Kutim, or by and for Samaritans, סוכה מכל מקום, Sukkah
mikol makom, whatever type of סוכה you make כשרה, kesherah, it’s kosher
ובלבד שתהא מסוככת כהלכתה, uvivalvad shetehey mesukhakhat kehilkhatah, as long as it’s
made with proper סכך, s’chach, as long as it’s done the right
parameters. We don’t care who made it and for what purpose it
was made, which is amazing. You don’t have to make your סוכה
for the sake of סוכות, as long as and it doesn’t have
to be made for a Jew to use, it doesn’t have to
be made for the sake of סוכות, as long as it’s not
where you live and it satisfies the right requirements, it’s kosher. So
גמרא says מאי כהלכתה? Mai kehilkhatah? What do you mean the סכך
s’chach is done correctly? Of course you need to do the סכך
s’chach correctly. So אמר רב חסדא והוא שעשאה לצל, Amar Rav Chisda
vehu she’asah letzeil,
it was made for shade. We do not require, this is very
important, we do not require that the סכך s’chach or any of
the סוכה be made for the sake of סוכה. It could be
made for some completely different purpose, even for animals, but in order
to have the designation of סכך, s’chach, it has to be made
for the purpose of shade. It’s not called סכך s’chach if it
wasn’t put up there to serve the purpose of shade. And this
דין din gets to the centrality of סכך s’chach as the identifier
of the סוכה, and its identity of סכך s’chach is something made
for shade. So as long as the סכך s’chach was put up
for shade, I don’t care what purpose the סוכה was made and
who made it, it’s kosher. And then גמרא just says
okay, and סוכה מכל מקום לאתויי מאי? Sukkah mikol makom le’atuyei mai?
What was that catchall category you said at the end, any type
of סוכה is fine? לאתויי סוכת רקב"ש, Le'atuyei Sukkot Rakbash, to include
סוכת רקב"ש. Sukkot Rakbash. What’s סוכת רקב"ש? Sukkot Rakbash? So we have
another ברייתא beraita דתנו רבנן, Detanu Rabbanan, סוכת רקב"ש. Sukkot Rakbash. So
what does each letter stand for? סוכת רועים, Sukkot Ro’im, if it’s
made by shepherds when they’re tending their sheep, סוכת קייצים, Sukkot Kayatzim,
or people that are watching the fruit that’s out in the field
that’s drying and they also move around and dwell in these huts,
סוכת בורגנין, Sukkot Burganin, or it’s made
by people that are going
to watch the city, city watches, and they’ll move around and dwell
in these סוכות, סוכת שומרי פירות, Sukkot Shomrei Peirot, or people that
watch the fruit, סוכה מכל מקום, Sukkah mikol makom, any type of
סוכה כשרה, kesherah, ובלבד שתהא מסוככת כהלכתה, uvivalvad shetehey mesukhakhat kehilkhatah, as
long as the סכך s’chach is right. מאי כהלכתה, Mai kehilkhatah, אמר
רב חסדא והוא שעשאה לצל, Amar Rav Chisda vehu she’asah letzeil,
making it for shade. Okay, so same idea, we don’t care why
it’s made for, what purpose it’s made for, as long as it
was made for shade it’s okay. Now סוכה מכל מקום לאתויי מאי?
Sukkah mikol makom le’atuyei mai? This list, which says any type of
סוכה, what’s it coming to include? לאתויי סוכת גנב"ך. Le’atuyei Sukkot Ganbakh.
סוכת גנב"ך, Sukkot Ganbakh, meaning one is a list of גנב"ך Ganbakh,
and says any type of סוכה even the רקב"ש Rakbash type, and
the other is a list of the רקב"ש Rakbash and says any
type of סוכה even the גנב"ך Ganbakh type. So which list do
you think is more important? So האי תנא דגנב"ך אלימא ליה גנב"ך,
Hai tanna de-Ganbakh alima leih Ganbakh, the one that starts with גנב"ך,
Ganbakh the גנב"ך Ganbakh cases are better סוכות. Why? משום דקפי, mishum
de-kfiei, they’re relatively permanent structures, maybe this goes into whether סוכה is
דירת עראי dirat arai or דירת קבע. dirat keva. So he says
even
though it was made for animals it’s okay, but you’re starting with
the idea that these are permanent structures, וקתני מכל מקום, vekatani mikol
makom, and not only that, even the רקב"ש, Rakbash, even מכל מקום
לאתויי רקב"ש דלא קפי, mikol makom le’atuyei Rakbash dela kfiei, the things
that are made for the shepherds and aren’t permanent, even that’s okay.
So the חידוש, chiddush, you start with גנב"ך and the חידוש chiddush
is even the רקב"ש Rakbash that’s not permanent.
והאי תנא דרקב"ש, Ve-hai tanna de-Rakbash, the other תנא tanna starts in
the opposite direction. אלימא ליה רקב"ש, alima leih Rakbash, רקב"ש Rakbash is
better דבני חיובא נינהו, de-vnei chiyyuvah ninhu, it’s made by and maybe
even for men. So it’s maybe that’s more obvious, I don’t care
it’s temporary, that’s more obvious, that’s for men and Jewish men, ותנא
מכל מקום, vetanna mikol makom, and not only is those kosher, even
the גנב"ך לאתויי גנב"ך דלאו בני חיובא נינהו, le’atuyei Ganbakh delav bnei
chiyyuvah ninhu, that’s made for people that aren’t obligated. So basically the
upshot being one list assumes one as the default, the other the
other, but everybody agrees that even if it’s very temporary and made
for moving around, but סוכה could be a temporary structure, and even
if it’s made not by and for people that aren’t obligated like
non-Jews, it’s totally kosher. It doesn’t have to be made for the
sake of סוכה, it doesn’t have to be made by somebody obligated,
it just has to be made for the sake of shade. And
we’ll end there and we
actually
finished.